曼德拉：1918.7.18－2013.12.5享年:95岁[去逝时本片在英国公演]
Penguin听译、校对、时间轴0202、配歌词 342635392@qq.com:4 RocL & peers
Olishasha...Olishasha...
此片据其狱中秘密撰写自传【曼德拉传：漫漫自由路】改编
本中英双语字幕供英语学习、字幕制做交流，禁用于商业，违者责任自负。正版高清。
I dreamed the same dream, night after night:
【旁白：南非口音英语】那时我总是做着同一个梦，一夜又一夜,
I am coming home to the house in Orlando.
我总是做梦回家，回到在奥兰多的房子。
【奥兰多镇8115号：南非索韦托市,曼德拉的第一个家】
Everything is the way it was.
一切依旧。
They're all there， all the ones that I have loved most in this world.
他们齐聚一堂，所有我在这个世界上的挚爱。
They seem fine getting along with their lives.
他们看起来都过得很好。
But, they do not see me.
但是，他们对我视而不见。
They never see me.
他们从来没看我。【梦如人生，人生如梦。】
[英译字幕] 科萨族的孩子们【科萨/哲豪萨语歌曲：成人礼】
[英译字幕] 孩子自由地奔跑吧。【科萨语歌曲】
[英译字幕] 但责任等待着他。【科萨语歌曲】
[英译字幕] 告别你的童年吧。【科萨语歌曲】
[英译字幕] 你们即将长大成人。【科萨语歌曲】
[Xhosa]Divine!Divine!
【科萨语】神圣的！ 神圣的！
Your youth, your duty, your strength, is not your's alone.
你的青春，你的责任，你的力量，不只是你自己一个人的。
You alone are small, your people are mighty. Now, go.
你独自一人是渺小的，而你的民族是强大的。现在, 去吧。
You are a man, live as a man.
你是个男人了，象像个男人活着吧。
Now I was a man, with duties to my people.
现在我是个男人，肩负我对民族的责任。
My father had given me the name Olishasha：Troublemaker.
我父亲曾经给我起了个科萨名Olishasha【奥利沙沙】：惹事生非者。【转眼成为青年】
I didn't want to make trouble.
我从来没想过要惹事生非。
I wanted to make my family proud of me.
我只想要光宗耀祖。
Hey, how are you?
嘿，你怎么样？
[Xhosa]Nejins
【科萨语/布尔语】？
[Xhosa]Orotacha
Hey, don't be naughty.
嘿，别淘气。
[Xhosa]This is your reward.
【科萨语/布尔语?】这是你的报酬。
英语字幕【南非・约翰内斯堡，1942年】
We're almost there.
【布尔语，南非荷兰语】我们快到了。
Out of my way，boy！
滚开，别挡我路，黑小子！
门上商号【"曼德拉与坦波"律师事务所】
Sorry，coming through. For you in 15 minutes，15 minutes.
对不起，让我过去。   找你15分钟后，15分钟。
Mr. Mandela you had promised us...
曼德拉先生你曾答应过我们。。。。。。
Yes.   People are losing their homes and lands.
是的。 人们正在失去他们的家园和土地。
How can I help you?   I am not a thief.
我能为你怎么帮你？   我不是贼。
[In courtroom] Mrs.De Kok，
【在法庭上】德・科沃科夫人，
My client, your former maid, has been accused of stealing these items of clothing from your bedroom.
我的客户，你的前女佣，被控从你的卧室偷窃了这几件衣物。
Am I to be spoken to like this by a native?
【非洲】土著人打算象这样对我讲话吗？
He is council for the defense,Ma'am.
他是被告的代理律师，夫人。
If you feel uncomfortable, you may address your answers to me.
但是，如果你觉得不舒服，你可以向我给出你的回答。
Like in your worship. Mrs.De Kok, how do we know that these items are not my client's herself?
象你在礼拜中一样。德・科沃科夫人，我们怎么知道这几件东西不是我客户她自己的？
I don't understand. What did he say?
我不明白。他说什么？
Well, what I'm saying is, can you identify these items as yours, Mrs. De Kok？
好吧，我说的是，你可以辨认出这些物品是你的吗，德・科沃科夫人？
Well, you seem...unsure.
啊，你看起来...不确定。
I will not be spoken to like this. It's disgusting！
我不允许这样给我讲话。这真让人恶心！
If I had known I was going to be so insulted in a court of law, I would never have come.
早知道我会被如此侮辱在法庭上，我就不来了。
Your Honor, I move... Yes, Yes.
法官大人，我提议... 好了，好了。
Case dismissed.
案件驳回。【不立案，被告：不被起诉=无罪。】
You must carry my bag, you're lazy.
你得给我提包，你个懒虫。
Madiba, I heard you're a man to watch.
大人,听说你值得观注。
【马迪巴Madiba：对部落贵族尊称】
Maybe I should sell tickets.
也许我应该卖门票。
You don't come to Congress meetings. Why would I want to do that?
你没来出席"非国大"会议。            我为什么应该想要做那事呢？
Do you know anything about us?
你知道我们吗？
You know anything about the African National Congress[ANC]?
你知道“非洲人国民大会党ANC【非国大】”吗?
If you went out today and said "follow me!" No，body would follow you.
如果你今天出去呼吁“追随我吧！”，没有人愿意追随你，
So, why should I?
所以，为什么我应该追随ANC？
Do you like it when the Boers are calling you 'boy'.
当布尔人【南非土生荷兰白人】叫你的"黑小子"时, 你喜欢吗?
When I'm better qualified, better dressed and richer than they are,
当我有更好的资历、更好的衣着并且比他们更有钱时，
they won't call me boy anymore.
他们就不会再叫我"黑小子"了。
You're right, we need him.
你说得对，我们需要他。
【沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu：南非黑人运动领袖】
【Lyrics:Oh beautiful country，Africa is second to none】
【歌词: 哦，美丽的国家，独一无二的非洲】
【There is a wild animal pasture...】
【有狂野生动物的大草原.....】
What does a hotshot lawyer know that I don't know？
一位大律师知道什么我不知道的东西？
I know the law says, you can only have relations with members of your own race.
我知道法律规定，你只能与你自己种族的成员有关系。
Am I a member of your race? It's a suggestion.
我是你种族一员吗？          只是个建议。
Mr. Nelson.  Here it is.
纳尔逊先生。 给你。
This is the official manner of establishing relation type.
这是确立关系种类的官方形式。
If the pencil stays in my hair,I'm a black man. Not me?
如果铅笔留在我头发里，我就是个黑人。            我不是？
The pencil stays in your hair. You're black and can officially have relations with me.
铅笔在你的头发里。你就是黑人因此可以正式地与我有某种关系。
Always watch...
总是要小心。。。。。。
Why say anything, come here.
为什么要说啥，来到这里。
Hey!
嘿!
Darling, my darling, let's wear my jacket.
亲爱的，我亲爱的，穿上我的外套。
In return, seal with a kiss
作为回报，给我一个吻吧。
Hi my friend. This woman, you can take her home for me
嗨，朋友。这个女人，为我把她带回家吧。
You're gonna be fine, man?  Never better.
你会没事吧，伙计？          没这么好过。
How many fingers? Ha, ha, ha!
多少个手指？      哈，哈，哈！
Bye.
再见。
Indian, that's what I'm talking about.
印度佬，这就是我说的。
Hey, you.　Where's your pass, hey?
嘿，你。你的通行证在哪儿，唉？
Ah, I left it at home, pass. No, no! You come with us. Come on, come with me.
啊，我落在家里了，通行证。不，不! 你跟我们走。快点，跟我走。
Hey, don't fight, come with me.
嘿，别打了，跟我来。
Come on, boy.
快点,小子。
Captain, he's got no pass. We'll put him in a cell.
队长，他没有通行证。我们把他关在号子里。
Quiet! Get up! Get up!
安静！起来！起来！
Get up! Come on.【Vomitting】  Hey, don't pollute my shoes.
起来！快点。    【呕吐】       嘿，别弄脏我的鞋子！
Get him up![Kicking] Ah~ ~
抓他起来！【脚踢】   啊～啊～
I say get up! Beat him. Enough...
我叫你站起来！揍他！够了。。。。。。
Jackson Glada questioned at JP station.
杰克逊・格拉德在JP警察局审讯。
Yes, no pass.
对, 因为没有通行证【暂住证?】。
Cause of death, gentle syphilis. Everything's in here.
死因:轻微梅毒。一切都在这儿。
No! He was beaten to death in JP station. I have the medical affidavits for his injuries.
不！他是在JP警察局被殴打致死的。我有证明他伤情的医生誓词。
Are you accusing the police of lying? I have medical affidavits.
你指控警方撒谎？ 我有他的医生誓词。
I suggest that you start showing some respect for the law, boy!
我建议你开始稍微显示点对法律的尊重，黑小子!
And I have work to do. Good day to you.
但我有事要忙。再见吧。
That's no law. There's no law for us.
这是无法可依。对我们来说：无法可依。
Who did Jackson ever hurt? What did he do to deserve what they did to him?   Thank you.
杰克逊伤害了谁？他做了什么？让他们这样对待他？                               谢谢。
And nobody cares, nobody cares a damn.
而且无人理睬。无人理睬艹TM！
What do you mean? Something has to change.
你的意思？        有些事情得改变。
How should that happen?Education.
那应该如何产生呢？教育。【教育救国......】
Hard work. Try it! No, no, Nelson.
努力工作。 试一下。不，不，纳尔逊。
You can't do it alone. None of us can
凭你一己之力是不行的。我们没有一个人可能。
There's me and that's you.
沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu：有我，还有你。
That's Oliver.
沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu：还有奥利弗。
and that's Kati.
沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu：而且还有卡蒂。。
And each one of us are to little to do anything.
并且我们每一个体太渺小，不足以成事。【革命导师：沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu】
But together, we have the power.
但团结起来，我们就有力量。【革命导师：沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu】
Smoke?
抽烟吗？
I don't smoke.
我不抽烟。
Do you think I should join the ANC?
你认为我应该加入ANC【非国大】吗？
I think you like to talk.
我认为你们喜欢吹水。
And what about you? What do you like to do?
那么你呢，你想做什么？【美女爱英雄。。。】
[Music plays]
[音乐播放]
[Horns]
[鸣笛]【伊芙琳・梅斯：虔诚的基督徒】
Brother.
兄弟。【沃特・西苏鲁Walter Sisulu：伊芙琳・梅斯的表哥】
You look gorgeous.
你看起来很漂亮。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Not until we're married.
在我们结婚前都不行。
That's it. That's it. One, two, here. Yes!
就这样，就这样。一，二，这边。对!
One, two.
一，二。
Now. Nice. Very nice. Is that all you got?
现在。好，很好。你就这点水平？
One, two.One, two.
一，二。一，二。
Where's the jab? Where's the jab?
猛击在哪里？猛击在哪里？
One, two.
一，二。
Ah, ah! Finish.
啊，啊。结束。
Harder. Okay, okay, stop!
再狠点。好了, 停!
You win.
你赢了。
Walter? Nelson!
沃特？纳尔逊！
I see you're working very hard. Here, let's fight.
我看你训练得非常刻苦。          看这儿，让我们斗争吧。
Tomorrow morning.  What's that?
明天早上。         那是什么？
Boycott the buses?
抵制公共汽车？
Yap! See you're talking to people about freedom and justice，they don't listen.
对!明白吗，给人们讲讲自由和公正。他们不会听。
But put their bus fare up by a penny,
但把他们的公交车票上涨1便士。
that they care about.
那他们就在意了。
Help me，Coach? Yes.
帮我一下，教练？ 是的。
Let me see. There you go.
让我看看。给你。
Bring your wife. Ah...
带上你老婆。     嘿。。。
【与伊芙琳1944年结婚,是沃特的表妹。】
Nelson, you can't work all night.
尼尔森,你不能通宵工作。
I'm going to bed now.
我要去睡觉了，现在。[发出信号...]
I'll come later.
我就来。【已经忘了儿女私情......】
Please give yourself a rest.
也得给自己休息一下。
You can't do everything. Leave some things to God.
你不能做了一切。留点给上帝。【伊芙琳・梅斯：虔诚的基督徒】
Does your God want our children to go hungry? Nelson!
你的上帝想让我们的孩子食不果腹吗？            纳尔逊!
I don't see your God caring for our people.
我没有看到你的上帝眷顾我们的人。
Seems to me that he's looking after the boss. Nelson!
我看起来他总照顾老板。                        纳尔逊!
Evelyn, go to bed，
伊芙琳, 睡觉吧。
go to bed.
睡觉吧【冷落：完全不理！】。
【伊芙琳・梅斯(1922-2004)曼德拉的第一任(1944-1957)妻:子13年】
Give us one. Stop the buses.
给我们一份。拦住公交车。
Boycott them, they can't oppress us.
抵制公共汽车!他们不能压迫我们。
People, don't ride the buses.
同胞们，不要坐公交车。
[Boer?]Listen, I want to talk to you. I just need 5 minutes.
[南非荷兰语?]听着，我想和大家谈谈。我只要5分钟。
Don't pay. Let their buses run empty.
别买车票！，让他们的公交车都空跑。
Don't listen to this guy. If we stand together，we can beat them.
别听这个家伙的。如果我们团结起来，我们可以战胜他们。
We can not pay anymore.  Let them pay.
我们不能再付出了，让他们付出【提得到报应】。
Let's walk to Johannesburg.
让我们走去约翰内斯堡。
[Mayibuye!]-- Africa!
Return!归还!--非洲!
[My Country, My country, my people, my hometown ]
【游行人群合唱：我的祖国，我的祖国，我的人民，我的家乡。】
There's gonna be trouble. I want to go home.
会出麻烦的。我想回家。
[吼声振天，人潮涌动]
I'm going with them.
我要和他们一起去。[投身黑人权利运动，分道扬镳......]
I'm not breaking any laws but I must go with them.
我不会违法，但我必须和他们一起去。
Nelson！  You'll be fine.
纳尔逊！ 你会没事的。
Let's fight！
让我们斗争吧！【找到战友:投身南非民主运动】
【Singing: Come together, my country, my people】
【溶入洪流  合唱：团结起来，我的祖国，我的人民 】
【索维托市(南非最大的黑人贫民窟)奥兰多镇,1948年】
[Radio1]The nationalist Party leader, prime minister Head Malan has been returned to power in recent elections.
[新闻1]南非国民党(1915-2005)领袖，总理丹尼尔・F・马兰[Daniel F Malan1874-1959][赢得]近期选举重返政坛。
[Radio2]The government intends to geographically separate the blacks from the whites, .
[新闻2]政府打算从区域上将黑人与白人分离，
a total enforced segregation
一种强化的【种族】隔离。
[Radio3]The new cabinet has pledged to a policy of uncompromising white supremacy.
[新闻3]新内阁誓将执行不折不扣的“白人至上”政策。
Ah,ah...
呵呵。
I think this is your new home.
我想这是你的新家。
We call for freedom of movement. Come join us.
我们号召人身自由。加入我们吧。
Here's our campaign bulletin listing forbidden places:White only post office, white only toilets...
这是我们运动清单上列明的【黑人】禁入地点：邮局白人专用，厕所白人专用？
In the townships, we can't tolerate this constant oppressive military presence.
在各地城镇，我们不能容忍这种常态化的、镇压性的[维稳]驻军。
Come on, Thembi.
快过来，桑贝。[马迪巴・桑贝基勒:曼德拉的大儿子生于1945]
Why should we obey their laws?
为什么我们必须遵守他们的法律？
We don't have a vote. This is not our government.
我们没有投票权，这不是我们的政府。
They're having a party and we are not invited. Yes.
他们搞了个Party[聚会]，而我们却没有被邀请。    是的。
So let's defy their unjust law.
因此，让我们蔑视他们不公正的法律。
What can they do? Throw us all in prison?
他们能做什么做？把我们所有的人扔进监狱里？
No. Let them！
不。让他们扔吧！
When we're all in prison, let them mind their own goats，
当我们都在监狱里，让他们照顾自己的山羊，
Clean their own houses，Haha
打扫他们自己的房子，    [哈哈！听众都理解！]
Wash their own clothes. Haha
洗他们自己的衣服，     [哈哈！听众都受感染！]
Thank you for listening.
谢谢你们倾听。        [演讲大师的范儿！]
Thank you,Thank you.
谢谢,谢谢。
Do not go to prison yet, Nelson.
先不要去坐牢, 纳尔逊。【战斗了再说.....】
Sweetheart.
亲爱的[甜心]
You think I don't know? Know what?
你以为我不知道吗？      知道什么？
Evelyn, it's a defiance campaign. I did it for all of us.
伊芙琳,这是蔑视运动。我所做的是为了大家。
You care about all the children in South Africa except your own. Hey...
你关心南非所有儿童, 除了你自己的。   嘿。。。。。
Are you seeing other women for them? Are you seeing your whores for them?
你也为他们在和别的女人幽会？你也为他们在和你的婊子幽会？
I know, Nelson! And I can't take it anymore. Evelyn, stop now!
我都知道，尼尔森! 我忍不了啦！伊芙琳, 别说了,现在！
You're going to burn in hell.
你会下地狱被烧死。【战斗开始......】
Shut up! Shut your mouth!
闭嘴！闭上你的嘴。
Shut your stupid mouth!
闭上你的笨嘴！【家暴......】
[VOICE:crying baby...]
[背景:哭泣的孩子]
Thembi, go to bed.
桑贝，去睡觉！
I can't stand this anymore. I'm sorry.
我不能也能再忍受这一切了！我很抱歉。【1955年第一次婚姻关系破裂】
The boers say our town is a slum.
布尔人【南非荷兰人】说我们的城镇是个贫民窟。
All the people that have homes are to be evicted by force.
有房子的人被暴力驱逐。【强拆！】
That's true!
的确如此！
Our town is to be bulldozed so they can build houses for the rich.
我们的城市将被推土机铲平，好让他们给富人建造房屋。
Let them try.
让他们再试试。
We say over our dead bodies:(Yes)
我们凭着死去的人发誓：      (是的)
Let them bring their bulldozers！
让他们把推土机开来！
Let them bring their army, we will fight for our homes.
让他们把军队开来！我们要为我们的家园而战斗！
Yeah!
没错！【鼓动家诞生！】
We will fight for our freedom！ Yeah!
我们要为我们的自由而战斗！是的。【标语：权力平等】
If they want a war，we will give them a war.
如果他们想要场战争，我们就给他们战争。
Yeah![Camera man...]
没错!【拍照"狗仔"】
[Mayibuye!]--Africa!
Return!归还!--非洲!
[Mayibuye!]-- Africa!
This way.
这边！
Whites only. Stop You!
白人专用的。你站住！【旗帜：抵制蔑视不公正的法律】
Come together.
一起来。
You can not get in!
你们不许进入的！【\人与狗不得入内】
Go get them!
去叫他们！【标牌：第一站台，欧洲人专用】
Don't let them through. Stop them!
不要让他们通过。拦住他们！
Faster, they're coming.
快点，他们来了。
Where are they? What do you think you're doing here.
他们在哪儿？你以为你们在这里做什么。
You see, ladies, no manners at all.
你们看看，女士们，简直没有礼貌！
Take your hands off. Let go of me. Come on. 40 days.
拿开你的手。让我走。快点。40天。
[Mayibuye!]Return! 。。。
归还!----。。。
Come on, we've got the power!
【铁窗外口号】快呀，我们有力量！
[Mayibuye!] Africa!。。。。
【窗外口号】Return!归还!----非洲!【1952年曼德拉第一次入狱。】
Are you here alone?
你一个人在这儿？
Yes.
是。
Mom doesn't know I'm here.
妈妈不知道我在这里。
Mom says you're not to live with us anymore.
妈妈说你不会再和我们一起生活了。【1955分居后，3孩子们与母亲生活】
Thembi, I know I've been away a lot. Too much.
桑贝，我知道我经常外出不在家。太多了。
But I'm doing it for all of us.
但是我所做的一切都是为了我们大家。
I want you to believe that.
我想要你坚信这点。
[SONG PLAYS]
歌声响起
Go.
去。
Madiba. Mama.
马迪巴。妈妈。
他们说你的妻子离开了你。【科萨语配英语字幕】
【曼德拉的第一次婚姻：与伊芙琳1944-1957生活13年】
而且他们还把你关进监狱。【科萨语配英语字幕】
1956曼德拉因黑人反种族运动被捕控“叛国罪”
这不是你父亲想要让你们过的生活。【科萨语配英语字幕】
妈妈，请听我说。【科萨语配英语字幕】
我们曾为你感到骄傲。【科萨语配英语字幕】
而你却忘记了我们。【科萨语配英语字幕】
为什么这些人要抓你？【科萨语配英语字幕】
咦？
妈妈，请你要理解那些法律不是正确的。【科萨语配英语字幕】
难怪你的妻子离开了你。【科萨语配英语字幕】
当你在监狱里，谁会承担你作为一个男人责任？【科萨语配英字】
当你在监狱里，【科萨语配英语字幕】
谁将照顾你的家庭？【科萨语配英语字幕】
【做宅男？还是伟人？这是个问题。】
Do you want a lift?
你想要搭车吗？【相识。。。】
Okay.
好呀。
Come please.
请来吧。
Do you always accept lifts from strangers?
你总是接受陌生人搭车邀请吗？【哎，3岁看老呀。。。】
You are not a stranger. You're Nelson Mandela.
你不是一个陌生人，你是纳尔逊・曼德拉。【天下谁人不识君？】
And you are Winnie Madikizela.
而你是温妮・马迪基泽拉。【相知】
How do you know?I made inquiries.
你怎么知道？我打探了一下。【58年版人肉...】
And what else did you find out?
你还发现了什么其它的？
That you work at the Baragwanath hospital and you're the first black social worker they ever had.
你在巴拉格瓦纳斯医院工作，你是他们聘的第一位黑人社工。
And you're the most beautiful girl I've ever seen
而你是我见过最美丽的女孩子。【中箭:寸步难行......】
It's just here.
【医院】就在这里。
Thank you.
谢谢。
What time do you finish?
什么时候你下班？
Six. I'll be here.
六点。我会在这里。【相约】
See you soon. Bye.
回头见。再见。【春风得意......】
You know, I've been finding out about you too.
你知道，我也一直在寻找有关于你的一切。
Yeah? Enhen. And what have you found out?
真的？嗯哼。你发现了些什么？
Your wife left you.
你的妻子离开了你。【58年版人肉搜索:很八卦】
I was away too much.
我也经常外出不在家。【有必须对她编这种理由吗？】
Never enough time.
时间总是不够用的。【你以为只是钱？】
There is no time.
是根本没有时间。【时不我待】
Only now. Only now？
只有现在。只有现在？【只争朝夕？】
Yes.
是。
What do you mean? When I was 7 years old,
你什么意思呢？当我7岁时，
my little sister started coughing blood and my mother，she, she begged God to save her，
我的小开始咳血，因此我母亲她乞求上帝拯救她，
but she died.
但却死了。
Ever since then, I've known：we have to save ourselves，
从那时起，我就知道了我们要拯救我们自己。
【女汉纸的强大心灵成长史！】
we have to live while we can. Haha...
当我们能活，就要好好活着。  哈哈......【要活在当Dang下！】
Winnie...
温妮。。。。。。【相恋。。。】
I heard you have a lot of girlfriends.
我听说你有好多女朋友。【八卦还很多。。。。。。】
I'm different.
我和她们不同。【宣布占领：历史上温妮是权力欲和占有欲极强的女人......】
Fun...True...
有趣..真的...
I was thinking I know a good dressmaker，
我在想我知道我一个好裁缝，
very good value.
非常超值。
Maybe you should go and see her.
也许你应该去看看她。
Maybe, I should.
也许，我应该。
Maybe you should go to Bizara and talk to your father.
也许你应该去集市和你老爸谈谈。
Maybe I should.
也许我应该。
Was that a proposal? If that's what you'd like.
这是求婚吗？如果这就是你想要的。
Is it what you'd like?
这也是你想要的吗？
More than anything in the world.
比世界上任何东西都更想要。
Is that yes?
那是同意吗？
Yes, yes, yes. Haha...
同意,同意,同意。哈哈。。。。。。
【曼德拉的第二任妻子(1958-1996):温妮・马迪基泽拉生于1936.9：现年78岁】
[奔跑儿童的欢笑]
My wedding....
我的婚礼。。。【当时曼德拉40岁，温妮22岁】
[奔驰的马匹，人欢马跑]
[部族的迎亲欢歌，载歌载舞的少女]
Good.[Tribe Wedding Ceromony]
不错。【部族婚礼欢歌】
Do you feel happy?
你觉得高兴吗？
Come on, he's coming.
快点，他来了。【历史上4天部族婚礼：只进行一半Mandela就进了监狱】
I am taller.
我长高了。
In Sharpeville, an industrial township, thousands gathered outside the police station
【字幕：沙佩维尔镇，1960年3月21日】广播：在工业小镇沙佩维尔，成千上万的人聚集在警察局外抗议
to protest against a new law requiring every African to carry a pass at all times.
新的法律要求所有非洲人要随身携带通行证
The bastard are ignoring us. Quickly send help right away.
这个混蛋不理我们。马上发出求救信号。
Listen! It's an uncontrolled crowd gathered here.
听着！我们这儿有失控的群众集会。
All must be getting in position.
所有人各就各位。
You must all disband immediately.
你们必须立即解散。
See what I'm doing with your ID?
看看我在用你们发的身份证做什么？
Stay away!
走开！
Silence!
肃静！
You’re doing your job fast enough. Tell them to move backwards!
赶紧做你的工作，告诉他们要后退！
All retreat as per my mark.
全部后退到我的标志线。
Get out of here! That's your final warning!
从这里滚开！这是给你们最后的警告！
Shoot them!
开枪射击他们！
Cease fire!
停止射击！【狂射示威民众25秒！】
Find their guns. Better find their weapons.
寻找武器。最好找到武器。【以便定为"恐怖分子"】
Do you see a weapon? Have you looked for weapons？
你看见的武器了吧？你找到了武器了吗？
[Radio 1]50 to a 100 people were killed and hundreds injured.
【广播1：50～100人被枪杀，数百人受伤。】
[Radio 2]...kill 69 Africans in the township of...[Radio 3]most of the victims were shot in the back.
【广播2：杀死69名非洲人在。。。。。。】【广播3：大部分受害人都是背部中枪。】
[Radio 4]...men, women and children were killed or wounded
【广播4：男女老幼被杀害或受伤】
...as a consequence of the desperate endeavor to preserve white supremacy.
成为保持白人霸权绝望努力的结果......
...an event that stunted the world.
......震惊世界的事件。
We no longer accept the authority of a state
我们不再接受政府的权威。
that makes war on his own people.
因为它向自己的人民开战。
I'll advise on my approach of what's next.
我将会通知以后【斗争】的方法。
I'm going underground.
我得转入地下工作。
All of my tasks have always been nonviolent.
我的工作始终以来一直是非暴力。
I've tried.
我已经尝试过了。
I can't any more.
我从此不可能了。【开始暴力反抗种族隔离】
北非ANC【非国大】训练营
[Dialogue]What Amarian? He's fine.
【电影对白】什么美国人？他很好。
What? Fine?
什么？好吗？
She is good looking. But you could give me Sophia Loren any day.
她好看。但是你随时可以给我看索菲亚・罗兰。
We're going to do this way，Yes.
我们将做到这一点。是的。
Speaking of our nation. Yes.
说说我们的国家。是的。
We are the people of this nation. Yes.
我们是这个国家的子民。是的。
But we don't have power. Yes.
但是我们没有力量。是的。
We don't have rights. Yes.
我们没有权力。是的。
We don't have justice. Yes.No.
我们没有公正。是的。没有。
South Africa now is a land ruled by the gun.
南非现在是枪炮统治下的土地。
Yes. There comes a time
是的。总会出现这样一个时刻
in the life of every nation,
在每一个国家的历史上，
when there remain two choices，
当只剩下两个选择，
Submit or fight？Yes.
要么屈服要么战斗？
Fight!You chose.
战斗!你们选择了。
Fight!Fight!Fight!
战斗!战斗!战斗!
Don't worry, we'll find him.
别担心，我们会找到他的。
And then we'll hang him.
然后我们绞死他。
You need a man to keep you warm at night, don't you?
你需要有一个男人夜晚给你温暖，不是吗？
【字幕】Liliesleaf立里斯里夫农场-非国大ANC安全之家。【南非共产党员白人戈德赖希名下农场】
Ramos, this is David. Can you take him to the domestic quarters?
拉莫斯，这是大卫。你可以把他国内部吗？
Yes, very well.
是的，好的。
In the tube of a ballpoint pen,
在圆珠笔的管子里，
you fit in a plug and more time you've got，
你多装入一个开关
an aluminium powder
再装入铝粉
mixed with a manganite powder,
混和上高锰酸粉
you could get this for washing litters.
你买这个来清洗垃圾。
when the acid reaches the mixture
当酸接触到混合物后，
it catalyses,
它起催化作用。【中学化学水平】
and you got...'bang'
然后就会。。。"砰！"【土制易燃引爆装置：危险勿仿！】
[报刊标题]曼德拉领导ANC【非国大】滑向暴力道路
Catty. It's Nelson.
恶毒.  我是纳尔逊。
They're calling me a terrorist.
他们说我是恐怖分子。
I need to set the record straight. Now, find a foreign journalist.
我需要更正纪录。现在，找个外国记者。
I want the world to know, that I've been accused of running away and not standing up for my beliefs.
我要让全世界知道，我被指控是逃跑而并非因为坚持自己的信仰。
Tell them that I will not give myself up to accommodate a government.
告诉全世界：我不会去自首，以满足政府。
I do not recognize
我也不承认
we've been forced to an armed struggle.
我们已经被迫进行武装斗争。
The decision was not taken lightly by myself,
这是是艰难的决定，对我是
or the people, or the ANC.
对人民是，对ANC非国大也是！
Ray Menly, Nightly News.
瑞・曼尼，晚间新闻。
I have a few questions for you Mr. Mandela.
曼德拉先生，我要问你几个问题。
If the government does not give in to the concessions that you want,
1.如果政府没有向你们要求的妥协让步，
will there be violence? There's violence now.
就会将会出现暴力？        现在已经出现暴力。
For 50 years, we've been talking peace and nonviolence.
过去的50年，我们一直在谈论和平和非暴力。
The government's reply is violence, armed attacks on unarmed and defenseless people.
政府的答复是暴力，武装攻击手无寸铁、无自卫能力的人民。
If you were asked, what would you do?
如果问您：你将怎么办？
Mr. Mandela, what is it your personal want?
2.曼德拉先生，你个人的要求是什么？
I want freedom.
我想要自由。
I have beautiful children, a beautiful wife.
我有群漂亮的孩子和一位漂亮的妻子，
I want them to walk freely in their own land.
我希望他们在自己的国土上自由行走。
Madiba, we must go.
马迪巴，我们得走了。
Hey, it's Daddy.
嘿，这是爹爹。
Hey, hey, hey...
嘿，嘿，嘿。。。。。。
Look at you. Look at you.
瞧你。瞧你。
It's okay. It's Daddy.
好吧。这是爹爹。
It's your Daddy. You want to run to Dad?
这是你的爹爹。你要跑到爹爹那里？
Come on, Creska.
科瑞斯克，快点。
Come. Come.
来吧，来吧。
What are you?
你怎么样？
Fine. I lost a new job.
很好。我丢了份新工作。
I'll see that you get some help. No.
我会关照你会得到帮助。不。
I'll be alright.
我会没问题的。
I knew how it would be.
我知道这一切怎么回事。
Fighting.
战斗
I hate them so much.
我如此痛恨他们。
Petrus didn't make it.
皮特斯牺牲了。
What happened?
出了什么事？
The detonator went off too soon.
引爆装置爆炸太快。
So sorry, Madiba.
非常对不起，马迪巴。
It's not safe here anymore.
这里不再安全了。
Time for you to move on.
该你转移的时间了。
You are in the wrong place...Police!
你走错地方了...警察！
Come on! Let's go.
快点！我们走。
Police! You in there!
警察！你在这里！
Come out in the street!
出来到在街上！
Search the place!
搜查此地！
Stop right there!
就地站着别动！
Drop him! Hold him!
放了他！抓住他！
Police! Come out quickly!
警察！快出来！
We got you.
抓住你了！
Somebody wants me.
有人要找我。
Hello, Mama Winnie!Hello, Mama Winnie! They got him.
喂，温妮妈妈！喂，温妮妈妈！他们抓他了
【英文字幕】南非比勒陀利亚,最高法院--司法大楼,1963(实为1964年4月20日)
Mandela! Mandela!
曼德拉！曼德拉！【标语：与我们的领袖同在！】
That's it, bitch!
就这样，婊子！
Wait, he can't come in. Don't touch me!
等等，他不能进来。      别碰我！
You can't take him in. Don't touch me!
你不能带他进去。       别碰我！
I'll be back, okay?
我就回来，行吗？
Good?
好吗？
Now wait with your sister. Okay?
现在和你妹妹一起等，好吗？
Amandla!-Ngawethu
Power政权!-To the people归民!
Mayibuye!--Africa!
Return!归还!--非洲!
Silence!
肃静！【这份长达176分钟著名"法庭宣言"录音现存于南非国家档案馆】
Quiet! Quiet!
安静!安静!【在被告席上曼德拉宣扬:愿献身理想,坚信南非将民主自由！】
My Lord, I call the case of the State against the national high command of Kontisiswe,
我的法官大人，我代表政府公诉“全国最高指挥部kontisiswe”【其名源于伊尔贡的犹太国家地下组织】。
the military wing of the African National Congress.
非洲人国民大会ANC的军事机构
The State contends that the accused are responsible for acts of sabotage
国家指控被告对以下行为负责：各种的破坏活动
and facilitating violent revolution and armed invasion of this country,
并推动暴力革命和武装攻击国家
with the intention of overthrowing the government.
阴谋颠覆政府。
Accused number one,
第一被告，
Nelson Mandela
纳尔逊・曼德拉
Do you plead guilty or not guilty?
你认不认罪?
My Lord. It is not I but the government that should be put in the dock.
我的法官大人，站在被告席的：不应该是我，而应该是政府,
I plead not guilty.
我：“无罪”。
The State has formally advised me
政府已经正式通知我了
that they'll be asking for the supreme penalty permissible by law, which is death.
他们一直要求执行法律允许的最高刑罚，即死刑。
Of his chances to attack the credibility of the charges, dispute any falsehood and challenge every charge,
现在看来，他的机会能质疑指控的真实性，争辩伪证的和拒绝承认所有指控，
we think they will bring a guilty verdict, but we might be able to avoid the death sentence.
我们认为他们将会判有罪，但我们或许可能避免死刑。
Agreed?
同意吗？
Agreed.
同意。
And be happy.
那么高兴点。
Smile!
微笑一下！
This may be the greatest service you ever do for our people.
这可能是你为人民做出的最好服务。
I want to thank you, Brent，
我要感谢你，布莱特。
for all that you have done for us,
为你过去为我们所做的一切，
for all that you are doing now
为你现在为我们所做的一切，
as for your own people.
正如为你为自己人所做的一样.
You're going to do something stupid, aren't you?
你打算做些傻事，不是吗？
We all agreed.
我们都同意了。
I'm gonna make a statement from the dock.
我打算在被告席上发表申明。
For God's sake, Nelson! If you make a statement from the dock,
看在上帝的份上，纳尔逊！如果您在被告席上发表申明，
you'll lose your right to be cross-examined.
这样你就丧失了向对方证人反讯问的权利。
You might as well admit the charges. I am admitting the charges.
你倒不如承认所有控罪。我都会认罪。
Show me this statement.
给我看看你的申明。
You damn fool!
你这该死的傻瓜！
Cut the last sentence at least.
删除最后一句话，至少。
Don't give it to them on a plate.
不要轻易地交给他们。
This is not for them.
这不是为了他们。
It's for our people.
这是为我们人民。
If I'm going to die, I want them to know why.
如果我就要死了，我也希望他们知道为什么。【著名的法庭申明开始！】
My name is Nelson Mandela.
我的名字是纳尔逊・曼德拉。
I'm the first accused.
我是第一被告。
I do not deny that I had planned sabotage.
我不否认我策划过破坏活动。
I did not planned it in the spirit of recklessness,nor because I have any love for violence.
但我不是在鲁莽中策划的，也不是因为我爱好暴力。
The hard facts of that 50 years of non-violence have brought the African people
残酷的事实是50年非暴力带给非洲人民的
nothing but more and more repressive legislations
只是越来越多的压制性法律
and fewer and fewer rights.
和越来越少的权利。
Africans want a just share in the whole of South Africa.
非洲人想要公平地分享整个南非。
We want equal political rights: One man, one vote.
我们想要平等的政治权利:一人一票。【全民普选】
I've dedicated myself to this struggle of the African people.
我一直全身心地投入非洲人的这一项斗争。
I have fought against white domination.
我反对白人霸权。
I have fought against black domination.
我反对黑人霸权。【超越种族，超越仇恨，超越血仇】
I have cherished the ideal of a free democratic society,
我一直抱有一个自由、民主社会的理想，【南非梦】
where all persons live together in harmony with equal opportunities，
在那个社会里: 各种族和谐生活，拥有平等的机会，
it is an ideal which I hope to live for and achieve,
这就是我希望为之而生存并要实现的理想
but if needs be,
但如果需要的话，
it is an ideal for which I am prepared to die.
这也是一个我准备为之献身的理想。【为民主自由献身】
Amandla!-Ngawethu
Power政权!-To the people归民!
Mayibuye!--Africa!
Return!归还!--非洲!
Before the judge imposes the supreme penalty, there is one more step.
在法官宣判极刑之前，还有一个程序。
He will ask the first accused Nelson, "have you any reason to advance
他会问第一被告纳尔逊，“你还能提出什么原因
where the death sentence should not be passed?"
不应该宣判死刑？
You could then say...I have nothing more to say.
然后你可以说...我再没有什么话要说了。
That would help your appeal.
这有助于你上诉。
There will be no appeal.
不会上诉。
No appeal? We've talked about this.
不会上诉？我们已经讨论过这点。
We are ready.
我们准备好了。
All rise!
全体起立！【最终宣判】
I've reached my verdict. The defendants will rise.
我已经做出判决。全体８名被告请起立。
The accused are all found guilty as charged.
被告全都如原控，被判有罪。
The accused have made high moral claims for their actions.
全部被告声称其行为基于崇高的主张。
In essence... they have entered martyrdom
实质上，他们已经为其信念殉道
at the hands of what they call their oppressors.
在他们称之为压迫者的手中成为烈士。
But I would not give them that satisfaction.
但我不会让他们就此圆满。
Let us show the world that we are a nation of laws
让我们向世界展示：我们是法制国家
and when possible we can pair justice with mercy.
并且我们尽可能让公正与仁慈同在。
I therefore decided not to impose the supreme penalty.
我因此决定：不判处最高处罚【极刑】
The sentence in the case of all their dues will be life imprisonment.
根据本案，数罪并罚，判他们的：终身监禁。
Amandla!-Ngawethu...Mayibuye!--Africa!
Power政权!-To the people归民!...Return!归还!--非洲!
【法庭斗争：全剧10分种的高潮！】
【英文字幕】罗本岛,1964年6月13日【南非开普敦近海】
Let's go down! Come. Hurry!
下来！来！赶快！
【从此，曼德拉开始了他27年的“监狱生涯”】
Go there! There!
去那儿！那儿！
Move! Move! Everybody!Get in line!
走！走！所有人!排好队。
Form a line there! Move!
站成一队！走！
You're not in Johannesburg anymore.
你们已经不在约翰内斯堡了【南非最大的城市】
You're not in Pretoria. You're on the island.
你们也不是在比勒陀利亚。你在岛上。
【南非行政首都，2005改称非洲名“茨瓦内”】
You'll never leave here again.
你们将永远不会离开这里。
You'll never touch a woman or a child again.
你们将永远不会接触到女人或者孩子。
You will die here.
你们会死在这里。
If you have any complaint, well that's just too bad.
如果你有任何投诉，哎呀，这就太糟了。
Because nobody on the island gives a shit.
因为这个岛上没人在意这种P事。
And nobody in the rest of the universe will ever know.
而全宇宙其它角落，也没人会知道。
It's a pity they didn't hang you.
可惜没有绞死你们。
I'm gonna make sure you wish they had.
我会保证你们希望：还不如早点绞死算了。
Move! Quick! Move! Go! Go! Move!
走！快点！别站着！走！走！别站着！
You'll wear this.
你穿上这个。
You need to get trousers. You need to get socks.
你们要穿上裤子。你们要穿上袜子。
Boys get shorts.
黑小子穿裤。
Put them on.
穿上短裤！
Well Kati, looks like you'll have to be the daddy.
凯蒂，看起来你得做的老爷了。
Don't talk! Move! Move!
别说话！走！走！
Put all your civvies here in the box. Move it.
把你们的便装都放在这盒子里！ 快点！
I'm watching you my friend.
我会注意你的，我的朋友。
Move it!
快点！
Go! Go! Move!
走！快！快点！
Mosoleli: Shut up! Keep going!
Mosoleli: 闭嘴！继续前进！
Natada！
Shut up!
闭嘴！
Here! Move, coolie!
这儿!快走! 苦力!【南非英语对印度及有色人种的蔑称】
You here. fast! Fast!
你在这里.快！快！
Mandela?
曼德拉?
Go!
进去！
This is it, boy. Home...for the rest of your life.
就这儿了，黑小子。家...你下半辈子的家。
Magreti, come, move!
Magreti，来，快点！
Magreti! Move!
Magreti! 走！
Sala, come!
萨拉，来！
...
Amandla!... Robben Island Birdview
Power!权力！...
罗本岛监狱鸟瞰【曼德拉在此作为政治犯被秘密囚禁18年,现为博物馆，旅游胜地】
Routine check.
例行检查。
Get out!
滚出去！
Stay where you are!
呆在那儿别动！
Get out of my bedroom!Get out!
滚出我的卧室！滚出去！
Hey! Hey! Hey! Quiet!Get out! Get out!
嘿！嘿！嘿！安静！滚出去！滚出去！
Jesus! Witch!
耶稣! 巫婆!   【温妮：狂暴的母老虎！】
Wake up! Wake up you slackers!
起床！起床，你们这群懒鬼！【早起与锻炼：活了95岁】
Come on! Up,Get up!
快点！起，起床！
Wake up! Come on, move!
醒醒吧！起床吧，行动！
Move! Hurry!
行动！快点！
Move!OK. Return to your place.
行动！好了，回到你的位置。
Listen! We're gonna start making demands.
听好，我们要开始提些要求。
And our first demand is going to be...long trousers.
而我们的第一个要求将是...长裤。
We have to make them respect us.
我们必须让他们尊重我们。
And they will, but it will take time. We have times.
而他们会的, 但这要点时间。我们有的花是时间。
So, we start small.
因此，我们从小的开始。
Okay. Come on，Move.
好。行了，快点！
Over there. Come on!
去那边。快点！
I got this. Move, Move!
做到这一点！快走！快走！
You there! Move! Move!
你那边！   快走！快走！
Come on!
快点！
Hey, you, boy!
嘿，你呢，黑小子！
What? Continue!
什么？继续！
Heard about your wife? Crazy woman!
听到你老婆的消息了吗？疯婆子！
Bitch!
泼妇！
Hey, we have no fighting.  Just do it, boy!
嘿，我们不打架。   尽管干呀，黑小子！
Please do it. Hey!
来干呀。嘿！
What is the problem here?
这儿有什么问题？
No problem！No problem, sir!
没问题，没问题，长官！
No problem!
没问题！
Let's work, boys! Go! Go!Go!Go!
干活去，黑小子们！走！走！走！走！
Get back to work. Every time they make us angry, they win.
回去工作。每次激怒我们，他们就赢了。
Never let them see you lose your temper.
永远不要让他们看到你发脾气。
Never! Hey! What are you looking at, Tendra?
永远不要！嘿，你在看什么，Tendra？
I want all of this done today. Back to work!
我要今天完成全部这些。回去干活！
[African?]For the sake of us!
[南非语言?]只为了我们的！【学会隐忍！】
Bring some here.
给这儿一点。【吃得饱！】
Hey![News clip]
嘿！【剪报：曼德拉被捕....其实判刑入狱-还有点愤怒.】
Number? 31159.
号码？31159。
Thank you,sir.
谢谢你，长官！
Number? 46664.
号码？46664。
That's category D. That's your allocation for the next 6 months.
是D类（丁类）。你下6个月就这些分到的信件。
Number?。。。
号码？。。。【打孔后整封信也只能看见署名：你的爱人温妮】
Wake up in there!
醒醒吧，在里面的！
Move, Let's move!
快点，都走了！
Get out! Now!
滚出去！现在！
Come on! Move!
快点！走！
You there! Move it!
你那！走了！
Stand in line! Strip!
排好队！脱衣服！
Strip! Get naked!
脱衣服！脱光了！
What I think of you is...you're nothing!
我把你们当什么？。。。你们什么都不是。
When I think of you in the morning, I think I'm in a shit man's house.
早上我一想到你们时，就想我在P人的家里！
You'll spend the night in the rain.
你们淋整晚上的雨。
Yeah! All night.
是！整晚上！
You're going to freeze!
你会冻死了！
You! Stand in line! Useless! Get up! Get up! Get up!Up!Up!Up!
你！站成直线！没用！起来！起来！起来！起！起！起！
You tell your commanding officer, I'll be complaining to the head of the prison system in Pretoria.
你向你的指挥官报告：我要向比勒陀利亚监狱系统的头头投诉。
You tell him that.
你向他报告！
Get up!
站起来！
You've got a complaint to make to Pretoria? Yes, colonel!
你要投诉给比勒陀利亚？                      是的，上校！
This prison is out of control.Those prison guards are nothing but drunk hooligans.
这座监狱失控了。这些看守不过是些醉熏熏的流氓。
What rights do they have to assault us？
他们有什么权利来侵犯我们？
Are you part of the justice system or gangsters in uniform？
你们是司法系统的一部分？还是群着穿制服的流氓？
You think you can scare me with this shit about Pretoria？
你以为你用比勒陀利亚之类的P事能吓倒我？
If those idiots don't like what I do, they just sack me. I don't need their job.
如果那些白痴不喜欢我方式，他们只要炒了我。我不要给他们打工。
My family's got 5 farms. I've got money!
我家有5个农场。我有的是钱！【官二代+地主+土豪！】
I do what I like!
我的地盘我做主！
Have you got anything else to say to me?
你还有其事情要给我说吗？
Yes, I put in a request for long trousers.
对，我提交了长裤子申请。
Long trousers?
长裤子？
He wants long trousers.
他想要长裤子。
[African]Together!
【南非语言号子】一二！一二！
Mandela! Follow me.
曼德拉，跟我来！
Speak English only, family matters only.
只准用英语交谈，只准谈家务事。
Any political talk and I'll terminate the visit. Sit!
如有任何政治交谈，那我就终止这次探监。坐！
Are you alright?
你好吗？
Yes, I'm alright.
是的，我还好。
Tell me about you.
谈谈你的情况。
I'm in their begging order.
我在他们的申请程序中。【温妮也在受到白人政府的迫害】
But don't worry.
但别担心。
Our friends are helping me.
我们的朋友们在帮我。【传递监内外黑人运动信息。】
The girls send their love.
女儿们向你问好。
They want to see you.
他们都想见你。
I think of them every day.
我每天都想念他们。
You must tell them I love them.
你一定要告诉他们：我爱他们。
They're not allowed visits until they're 16.
要到年满16岁,才允许他们探监，
Zindzi is not yet 5.
津泽还不到5岁
【另译“津荠”生于1960.12。精通法语，诗人，曼德拉和温妮的第二个女儿】。
Tell me about the arrest. It's nothing I can't deal with.
给我说说你被捕的事。这不是我不能处理的事。
They like to have little chats with me.
他们想和我“聊聊天”。
Usually they wait 'til just before the girls come back from school to take me away...
通常他们会等到正好女儿们放学回家之前带走我...
so the girls would find an empty home.
好让女儿们会发现家里空无一人。
They think about these things，you know.
他们算计这些事情，你懂的。
They think about me a lot.
他们算计我很多回。
Not too battered?
很受打击吧？
By hiting them！ And don't tell me I'm wrong, it keeps me strong.
因为打他们！请别告诉我错了，这让我坚强。
Hey! Family matters only.
嘿！只准谈家务事！
Your mother may depart. She is sick.
你的母亲可能要离开了。她病了。
They say she will die soon.
据说她快要去逝了。
【曼德拉的母亲1968年到罗宾岛探视过，不久病逝。】
I failed her. No.
我辜负了她。没有。
She understands and she's proud of you.
她理解，并且她为你骄傲。
Is that true? She told me so herself.
是真的吗？她亲口对我这样说的。
Mandela, let's go.
曼德拉，走吧。
Don't touch my kids!Mama!
不要碰我的孩子们！妈妈!【虎毒不食子！】
不要碰我的孩子们！妈妈!ss【别惹母老虎！】
Mama!
妈妈！
Mama will come back!
妈妈会回来的！
Get in the car.
上车！
Mama!
妈妈！
Ma...
妈...！
Where are my children? Where are my children?
我的孩子们在哪里？我的孩子们在哪里？
Where are my children? What have you done to my children?
我的孩子们在哪里？你们对我的孩子们做了什么？
Where are my children? Where are my children?
我的孩子们在哪里？我的孩子们在哪里？
我的孩子们在哪里？ 我的孩子们在哪里？
My darling daughters, I have been told that our beloved mama
我亲爱的女儿们，我听说我们心爱的妈妈
has been arrested again.
又再次被捕。
This is hard for me because I am the source of all your troubles.
这让我难受，因为我是你们所有麻烦的根源。
Mandela! Move!
曼德拉！走！
All that I wish for you to bear in mind is that we have a brave
我期望你们要记在心理：我们有一位勇敢
and determined mother who loves our people
坚定的母亲，她热爱我们的人民
with all of her heart.
全心全意。【因此温妮被尊称为“黑人母亲”】
When you are grown up, you'll understand how she has sacrificed her own happiness
当你们长大成人后，你们就会明白她为此牺牲了多少自己的幸福
in the battle for truth and justice.
以便为真理和公正而战斗。
I'm only allowed to send you 2 letters a year.
只允许我一年给你们寄两封信。
I am told you have not been getting them.
我听说你们还没有收到这些信件。
But I shall keep on writing. There are so little I can do for you.
但是我还是要坚持写。我能为你们做的事情很少。
These letters are the only means of passing my love to you.
这些信件是唯一能传递我关爱的方式。
[Boer]Open! The mouth!
[南非荷兰语]张开！嘴！
Upward!
向上！
Got to take a leak. That's too bad.
要去小便。太糟糕了。
You have to do something for us.
你得先为我们做点事情。
Then you could go back to your children.
然后你可以回到你孩子身边。
I pissed on you.
我尿到你了！【我鄙视你。】
Whore!Son of Bitch!
婊子！狗娘养的。
No!
不！
I dreamed about Willy last night.
我昨晚梦见了Willy.
Thembi was there too. He's living right there in Cape Town.
廷比也梦到了。他恰好就住在开普敦。
【南非第二大城市，南非立法首都,2011年估计370万人口】
Maybe, he'll come and visit you one day.
也许，有一天他会来探视你。
【曼德拉的大儿子廷比Thembi从没有探视:家暴、离婚...】
It's not been easy on the boy.
这一切对男孩子不容易的。
You terrorists, the most dangerous men in Africa.
你这群恐怖分子，非洲最危险的人。
You're a bunch of wild animals.
你们就是一群野兽。
Wild animals, a lot of you.
野兽，你们一大堆呀！
Now I'm in a zoo.I see myself more like a lion.
嗨，我在动物园。我看自己更像头狮子。
A tiger...No tigers in Africa, my dear.
老虎。。。非洲没有老虎，亲爱的。
Who told you that? It's a fact, there never were tigers here.
谁告诉你的？事实如此，从来没有狮子在这儿。
There are African tigers, kid.
有非洲虎的，屁孩！
What kind of lawyer is a tiger? Lawyers are cheetahs, Madiba.
什么样的律师是老虎。律师是非洲猎豹，马迪巴。
Go!Go!Go!
走！走！走！
Hurry up. Move!Move!Move!
快点。快走！快走！快走！
Hey，boy.
嘿，黑小子。
You think you're smart, don't you?
你自以为你很聪明，不是吗？
Can't be that smart otherwise I wouldn't be here.
也没那么聪明,否则我不会在这里。
You're gonna be on this shit island for the rest of your life.
你将在这狗P岛渡过你的余生。
I'll be gone in a year.
我一年后就要走了。
Why wait so long?
为什么要等这么久？
I mean your family have 5 farms.
我是说，你家有5个农场。
You've got money and you don't need this job.
你有的是钱，而且你不需要这份工作。
Who told you that?
谁跟你说的？【这个猪头很健忘：难怪炒他！】
You did.
你说过呀。
Move, Move!Long trousers!trousers!
快！快！　　长裤子！　　长裤子！
Long trousers!Long trousers! Madiba!Madiba!
长裤子！长裤子！    马迪巴！马迪巴！
Long trousers!
长裤子！
Can you believe it!
你能想念吗？
Kati, you're no longer the daddy.
Kati，你不再是一个老爷了。
Congratulations!
恭喜！【监狱中维权胜利：有了长裤, 换了监狱长】
Telegram!
电报！
Have you read?
你看了吗？
电报内容：请通知通知纳尔逊・曼德拉他的儿子桑贝(7月)13号因车祸当场去逝。--开普敦:曼德拉・利维.
[马迪巴・桑贝基勒:曼德拉的大儿子1945-1969年，年仅25岁,留下2儿子。]
It is my first born son.
这是我的长子。
It is my duty to bury him.
安葬他是我的责任。
To be honest, you're not to leave the island,never.
说句实话，你不会离开这个岛,永不。
I'm sorry, that's just... the way it is.
对不起，这就是。。。现状。
Madiba, what's wrong?
马迪巴，出了什么问题？
Madiba
马迪巴?？
I can't lose them anymore:
我不能再失去他们了:
my mother,
我的母亲、
my son,
我的儿子、
my wife.
我的老婆。
Come, now.
来吧，现在。
【英文字幕：1970年9月14日, 在被单独囚禁16个月之后】
[欢呼]标语：终于自由了！回家了！
[群众欢呼，记者拍摄] 标语：我们爱你!终于回家!欢欣回家！
【因妻子温妮・曼德拉的不屈不挠，使曼德拉的名字在70-80年代国际闻名】
Zindzi.
津荠
Winnie, talk to us，are you gonna make a statement?
温妮:告诉我们，你打算发表一个申明吗？
I say to my jailers, thank you.
我要对我的看守们说，谢谢。
And I say to the government, thank you.
我要对政府说，谢谢。
You helped me grow up.
你们帮助我成长。
I was very young when I married Nelson.
当我嫁给纳尔逊时，我还非常年轻[22岁]。
I'm not young anymore.
我不再年轻了。【此时34岁】
And I'm not afraid anymore. Yeah!
并且我不再害怕了。          好呀。
Amandla!--Ngawethu
Power政权!--To the people归民! 一呼百应!
[游行标语：抵制南非种族隔离政府！抵制奴隶货车司机！]
【橙子上英文：南非出口  酒瓶上英文：南非祖鲁出口】
【英文字幕：索维托，1976年6月16日 】
【示威标语：废除"阿非利卡语(南非荷兰语)教学"！释放学生！】
You Nelson Mandela?
你纳尔逊・曼德拉?
Yes.
是。
This is what you do?
这就是你在干的事？
This is what I do.
这就是我在干的事.
I told you these old men had given up.
我告诉你，这些老家伙们已经放弃了。
You must show respect to him.
你必须对他表示点尊重。
Respect? They're killing us on the streets.
尊重？他们在街道上屠杀我们。
【1976.7.16索韦托惨案:约176人死亡，1228人受伤】
Even the children are fighting back and he grows tomatoes.
甚至孩子们都在还击，但他却在种西红柿。
What is your name? My name is Patrick Lekota.
你叫什么名字？我叫帕特里克・莱科塔。
【生于1948.8.13，历任ANC情报局长1991，ANC主席1997-2007，1999为南非国防部长，2008脱离ANC成立人民大会党主席，2009失去主席职位,2014重新成为党主席】
Mr. Lekota, we've been in prison for a very long time and would be very happy
莱科塔先生，我们已经在监狱中被关押了很长时间所以我们会很高兴
to listen to you, to learn.
向你倾听，向你了解。
We closed down the schools, all the schools.
我们关闭了学校，所有的学校。
It was no ANC. We don't need your ANC.
这不是ANC。我们不需要你们的ANC。
【背后策划为South African Students Organization 南非学生组织SASO:9人被控“颠覆政府罪”】
I can see that you are very brave.
我可以看到你很勇敢。
And you...
你也是...
But alone, what can you do?
但是单独一人，你能做什么？
Together we have power... together.
团结起来,我们才有力量。。。团结。
You and I can be killed, imprisoned
你和我可以被杀死，被监禁。
but the organization goes on...
但组织会继续运作。。。
forever
永远
[南非语：有11种官方语言。。。。。。]
Did Brent do well in his examination?
Brent的考试还好吗？
Not too bad.
还不太糟糕。
How about Zena? Should be her 14th birthday soon?
Zena怎么样？快到她的14岁生日了？
Yes, July. Did you ever forget anything?
是的，7月。你忘过什么事吗？
【他俩友谊也拍过电影。】
Last time I saw Zindzi, she wasn't even 3.
上一次我看见津泽，她还不到3岁。
Zindzi！
津泽！
You are so beautiful！
你长得这么美！
I think of you every day but it is still the little girl that I see.
我每天都想念你，但只是我见过的那个小姑娘
And now you have grown to be a beautiful young woman.
现在你成长为美丽的年轻女子。
How's your mother?
你母亲怎么样？
You know mama, she's a fighter.
你知道妈妈，她是位战士。
And you? I'm your daughter.
你呢？我是您的女儿。
I want to fight too.
我也要战斗。
Please "no politics".
请勿谈政治。
That is not politics. That is my life.
那不是政治，那是我的生活。
You have your mother's spirits.
你有你母亲的精神。
Can I touch you? There's no physical contact.
我能摸摸你吗？不允许身体接触。
You do touch me.
你真的打动我了。【touch双关语:触摸、打动、感觉、感动】
But I want you to know that I always loved you.
但我想让你知道我到一直爱着你们。
Even without knowing you, I always supported you and I always believed that one day you'll be free.
尽管不认识你，我总是支持你。并且我总是相信你终有一天会自由。
We'll be able to touch.
我们会有接触的一天。
You must tell friends, that I am strong...
你必须告诉朋友们，我依然坚强的。【小通信员。。。】
and full of hope,
并满怀希望。
and eager to do whatever is asked of me.
而且热切想做要求我做的一切。
I'll tell them. They're waiting for you. We're all waiting for you.
我会告诉他们，他们在等待您。我们都在等您。
We're winning support all over the world.
There's gonna be a new campaign...Free Nelson Mandela.
我们正赢得全世界的支持。将会有一个新的“释放纳尔逊・曼德拉”的活动。
And I wanted it so soon. And it'll comfor all of us.
我希望这快点，这会安慰我们所有人。
It's no rumor, it's happening.
这不是谣言。这是正在发生的事件。
[Bishop]South Africa needs Nelson Mandela!The World needs Nelson Mandela!
【图图大主教】南非需要纳尔逊・曼德拉!世界需要纳尔逊・曼德拉!
图图大主教：1984年获得诺贝尔和平奖
Free Nelson Mandela!
【标语】释放Nelson Mandela！国际上呼声高涨!
Better stay home, brother.
你最好回家,兄弟。
The revolution will put you in the driver seat.
The revolution will be live.
革命会让你坐上驾驶座。革命会是现场直播。嘿。
【英文字幕：1982年3月31日夜开普敦,波尔斯摩尔监狱,在罗本岛上18年后】秘密转移。。。。。。
Welcome to the penthouse.
欢迎到顶层豪宅.
Hey, that's great. We all slept in the same room.
嘿,太好了。我们都睡在同一个房间。
Yeah.Then I'm putting in for a transfer
是的。然后把我申请转移
for medical reasons.Walter snores like a donkey.
鉴于医学的原因。沃特打呼噜像头驴。
Be Careful!
小心点！
That is what I called a big mirror.
这就是我讲过的"大镜子"。
【国家情报局的监视阴谋】
Ah, look at us.
啊，看看我们。【监视我们】
Dangerous tonight, each one of us.
今晚危险，我们每个人。【双方都懂的】
I used to have a good right hand.
我过去右手很猛。谢谢你。
[南非语歌舞]。。。。。
Thank you.
谢谢。
[南非语歌舞]。。。。。
Amandla!--Ngawethu!Amandla!--Ngawethu!
[南非语口号]Power!政权!--To the people归民!
The army is in our townships，
军队在我们镇上，
killing us every day.
每天都在屠杀我们。
But, we will fight to the last drop of our blood.
但是我们将战斗到我们的最后一滴血。
We have no AK-47s.We have no gas masks, but we have our hands.
我们没有AK-47步枪，没有防毒面具，但我们有双手。
We have children.
我们有孩子。【子又生孙，子子孙孙】
We have boxes of matches. We have matches.We have petrols.
我们有很多盒火柴。我们有火柴。我们有汽油。
We know the informants..
我们知道那些线人。
We know the traitors.
我们知道那些叛徒。
We know what to do with them.
我们知道怎么对付他们。
Before their bodies were set alight.
在他们点燃尸体之前，
[温妮至今仍然受到当时的一些命案指控和判刑.]
I am prepared to release Mr. Mandela,
我打算释放曼德拉先生。
if he would say that he rejects violence as a
如果他声明他反对使用暴力作为
means to reach and to achieve political ends.
追求和实现政治目的手段。
Does he think we are idiots?
他以为我们是白痴吗？
Anyone can see it's just another trick.
任何人都可以看出这只是另一个诡计。
Yes,Kati, it is a trick.
是的，Kati, 这是一个诡计。
But this is how it begins.
但是，这就是契机。
I call it a "contact visit". You can touch.
我叫它“接触性探监”。你们可以触摸。【1984.5.12】
I haven't touched my wife for 21 years.
我没有触摸过我妻子：已经21年了。【1963-1984】
You haven't changed.
您还没有改变。
I have.
我变了。【1984-1936=48岁了！】
To me，you haven't changed.
对我而言，您还没有改变。
Be careful with this offer of release！
小心这个释放的提议！
They're using you.I know.
他们在利用你。    我懂的。
You mustn't betray our people fighting on the streets.
你千万不要出卖在街头战斗的人民，
Speak loud so I can hear you.
讲大声点，好让我能听清楚你们。
Our people have never lost hope.
我们的人民从未失去希望。【果然好大声...】
The more they oppress us，the harder we'll fight.
他们越是压迫我们，我们越激烈战斗。
They fear us, Nelson?
他们害怕我们吗，纳尔逊？
They fear me.
他们害怕我
They think you're old and tired. Make them fear you too.
他们认为你又老又疲惫。要让他们也害怕你。
No politics.
不准谈政治。
We must talk politics. The president has given me an offer and expects a reply.
我们必须谈政治。总统已经给我了提出了条件并等待一个答复。
For the president in my name.
这是以我名义给总统的【答复】。【又夹带了。。。。。。】
【英文字幕】奥兰多体育场，1985年2月10日
[全部欢呼]
Halt, my Friends. She's Mandela!
暂停，朋友们。她是曼德拉！
On Friday, my mother saw my father in Pollsmoor prison.
在周五，我母亲在波尔斯摩尔监狱里见了我父亲。
She got his answer to president Botha's offer of conditional release：
母亲拿到他对博塔总统“有条件释放”的答复：
My father says
我父亲说
I'm not a violent man.
我不是一个暴力的人。
It was only when all other forms of resistance were no longer open to us that we turned to armed struggle.
只是当所有其它抵抗形式不允许时，我们才转向武装斗争。
Let president Botha renounce violence.
让总统宣布：放弃使用暴力。
Let him dismantle apartheid.
让他：取消种族隔离
I can not and will not give any undertaking at a time when
目前我不能,且将不会做出任何承诺
I and you the people are not free.
因为我和我的人民还不自由。
Your freedom and mine can not be separated.
你们的自由和我的自由：密不可分。
I will return.
我一定会回来的。
[会场沸腾]【\二代成长，呼风唤雨。。。】
Where are we going?
我们要去哪里？
Well.
啊哈。
Welcome. My name is Kobie Coetsee, I'm the Minister of Justice.
欢迎。我是科比・科特西，我是司法部长。【1986年开始谈判】
This meeting is about in place，
会议即将开始。
The rest of the world thinks South Africa will be ripped apart by a race war.
世界其它地方会认为：南非将被种族战争撕裂。
Now, we have to do something
现在，我们得采取行动
to restore confidence.
来恢复信任。
Let me introduce to you, General Williamse who you know.
请容许我给你介绍: 威廉姆斯将军，你也认识。
Fanie Van Der Merwe, Prisons Department. How do you do?
范尼・范・德・莫维，监狱部长。初次见面多关照！
Dr. Niel Barnard, National Intelligence Service.
尼尔巴纳德博士, 国家情报局
Pleased to meet you，Mr. Mandala.
很高兴见到你，曼德拉先生！
We 5 are charged by the President to find a way out of our current difficulties.
我们5个人受总统委托来寻求方法，以解脱当前困境。
Are you sure that you can talk to me？
你们确定你们能和我谈判吗？
I am a member of a banned organization.
我是一个被取缔组织的成员。
Now we'll talk to you if you can talk to us.
现在我们将和你们谈判如果你能和我们谈判。
Well, gentlemen...
那么，先生们,
Shall we begin?
我们要开始吗？
I don't trust them. This is not the time to talk.
我不信任他们。这也不是商谈的好时间。
I don't think Madiba should be talking to them on his own.
我认为马迪巴【曼德拉】不应该独自与他们谈判。
Let's just put it to a vote. I propose “No non-violence talks”.
让我们投票表决吧。我提议：不进行“放弃暴力”的谈判。
And you Walter?
而你呢，沃特？
None of us
我们没有一个人
that belong to the movement.
属于该运动。
4 against 1, motion carried.
4对1，提议有效。
I take note, comrades.
我记住了，同志们。
But I will do what I believe is right.
但我会做我坚信正确的事。
You have the most powerful army in Africa,
你们拥有非洲最强大的军队，
there is no way we could imagine a battle.
因此我们不能想象任何战斗。
But we have 30 million people,I would call that a stalemate.
但是我们有3000万人民，我把这叫僵局。
【2014南非人口：约5000万。】
Alright，here's the bottom line.
好吧，这就是底线：
You end the violence and we'll give you a share of the the power.
你停止暴力，然后我们让你分享一部分权力。
A share?
一部分？
Well, obviously, we can't accept a crude 1-man 1-vote system.
唉呀，很显然，我们不能接受粗糙的一人一票制度。[否定普选]
Yeah, if the blacks take over,our country is finished.
是呀，如果黑人接管，我们国家就完蛋了，
We are finished.
我们就完蛋了。
Why?Why?
为什么？为什么？
If the blacks take over.
如果黑人接管
Can you imagine what the blacks would do to us if they got us in their power.
你能想象黑人会怎么对待我们吗，如果他们掌权控制我们？
I am black. You're different.
我是个黑人。你不同。
That is why we are talking to you.
这就是我们和你谈判的原因。
They are the same people that put him in jail,
他们是同样的人:抓他进监狱、
that persecuted his wife,that murdered his friends...
迫害他的老婆，还杀害他的朋友们。。。
and he's talking to them.
但是他还和他们谈判。
I don't believe you don't want revenge.
我不想信你不想报仇。
You're right, I do.
你说得对，我想。
So, how can we ever allow you to have any real power.
所以，我们怎么可能竟然容许你掌握实权？
Well,I admit I want revenge, but I want something more than that，
虽然，我承认想报复，但我想要的比报复更高远，
That is to live without fear and hatred.
那就是：平安生活，没有恐惧，没有仇恨。
Sweet dreams, Mr. Mandela.
甜美的梦想呀，曼德拉先生。
I have no choice.
我别无选择。
I've seen what fear has done to your people：
我已经看到了恐惧已对你们造成了什么影响：
You've always been afraid of us, and it has made you an unjust and brutal people.
你们一直以来都害怕我们，而害怕让你们变成不公正、残酷的人。
Now, consider our position.
现在，考虑考虑我们的立场。
We know that one day we will be free,
我们知道，有一天我们会释放。
and we will be the rulers of our country.
然后我们将成为我国的统治者。
But do we want to live in the same hell as you do now？
但是，我们想生活在同一个地狱吗，象你们现在一样？
That would be to lock us back into prison,
那不是把我们又锁进监狱一样,
and our children, and generations after that.
连同我们的孩子，和子子孙孙, 万劫不复。
Gentlemen, look, I can tell you from nothing.
先生们，瞧，我能告诉你们，所无凭无据，
When we come to power, there will be no revenge.
当我们掌权，不会有报复。
[Screming，Shooting]
[尖叫,扫射]
Blacks continue to be the victims of this unprecedented wave of unrest.
[播音员]黑人断续成为史无前例的骚乱的受害者。
Nearly 300 people have died since September and only one white has been killed.
自九月以来300人死亡，但只有1名白人被杀。
Police shot from their armored personnel carriers. No rubber bullets here, these were live rounds they are firing.
警察从装甲运兵车中射击。这不是橡皮子弹，都是实弹射击。
Lay him there.
把他放在那里。
[Crying in African language...]
[南非语言哭喊...]
He's gone, Sissi
他去了，茜茜。
Make them suffer, as we suffer.
让他们痛苦，象我们一样痛苦。
Well, you impressed them.
嗯，你给他们留下深刻印象了。
I think we can make progress.
我认为我们可以取得进展步。
I hope so.
我希望如此。
I believe you will soon be reaching your 70th birthday.
我想你很快就会到70岁生日了。
My congratulations.
我祝贺你！
Do you plan a celebration?
你计划庆祝吗？【他在暗示什么？】
Nothing of consequence.
无关紧要。【这叫此地无银.....】
【英文字幕】温布利大球场,1988年【6月11日】
[Song: Free Nelson Mandela]
【歌曲：释放纳尔逊・曼德拉！】
[Song: Free Nelson Mandela] by British musician Jerry Dammers
【歌曲：释放纳尔逊・曼德拉】作曲英国音乐家杰瑞・达a斯
【T恤衫文字：对种族隔离说NO！】
释放纳尔逊・曼德拉音乐会：向全世界67个国家6亿人电视转播
Is this my new prison?Yep.
这是我的新监狱吗？是的。
Who else is to be held here? Just you.
还有谁会关押在此？只有你。【政府新阴谋--软禁：隔离、监视、控制、利用...】
Ah, Mr. Mandela welcome to your new home.
啊，曼德拉先生欢迎到您的新家。
Am I being fattened for the kill?
我正在被催肥待宰吗？
No. You have a vital job to do for your country.
不。你有了一份为国效劳的重要工作。
We'd look after you.
我们要"照顾"你。
By the way, the members of your family can visit anytime.
顺便说一句，你的家庭成员可随时探视你了。
Oh! A new kid.
哦，一个新宝宝。
Look
看看...
Are you're hungry? You have a hungry face.
你饿了吗？看来是一脸饿相。
Don't make a mess.
别搞乱了。
[African Language]What are you doing I'm very proud.
【非洲科萨语】你所做的一切我非常自豪。
I know that it has been tough for you, but...
我知道这对你来说一向很坚难，但...
I hear so much these things.
我听了很多这样的事。
These boys that you have around you. What about them?
那些在你身边黑小子们。他们怎么了？
The violence for one...
第一个：使用暴力。。。
Some of it may be necessary, but...
其中一些可能必要，但是。。。【注意到：两个小孩】
Hey！
嘿！
Is that for me?
那动作是做给我看的吗？
No, Guru. It's for the white men.
不，导师。是给白人的。
So, you're doing that because of the colour of their skin?
所以你们这么做，只因为他们皮肤的颜色吗？
Yes, Guru.
是的，导师。
That is what they do to us.
那就是他们这样对待我们的。
But we must do better.
但我们必须做得比他们更好。
Understand? Yes, Guru.
明白了吗？是的，导师。
Come, come on.
来, 快点！
These are my grandsons...
这些是我的孙子...【领袖身教：种族接纳、和解】
They want to meet you.
他们想见见你们。【温妮转身离去。】
Is Bobby there?
波比在吗？
No, no. I want to do this.
不，不。我想做这些事。【洗碗.....】
These are also dirty.
这些很脏。
[Tape Recoding...] It's in the agreement she can stay over night. Anytime that you want.
[录音中...]同意她可以留宿。任何时候都行。
That's not what she wants. This is still a prison.
这不是她想要的。这依然是一个监狱。【软禁！】
She can't pretend that I'm a free man.
她不能假装我是个自由人。
Okay.
好吧。
But she's still your wife.
但她仍然是你妻子呀。
Well, I was married in 1958,
哎，我结婚是1958年。
arrested in 62, didn't touch her again until 84.
被捕在62年，再没接触她直到84年。【22年】
Well,She is still my wife.
嗯，她仍然是我的妻子。
I've seen you with her when you looked at her photograph.
我看你在看她照片中时，你们在一起。
You love her.
你爱她。
That's the vey trouble, my friend, I never stopped loving her.
那正是麻烦所在，我的朋友，我从来没有停止过爱她。
But I love what she was. [Recording...]
但我爱是过去的她。【全程录音...分歧和绯闻的来源.】
The first step to regain the confidence of the markets is your release
恢复市场信心的第一步是您的获释。
and then of course the release of your colleagues.
而后当然是，释放你的同事们。
We've briefed the president. He's a pragmatist, he heard us.
我们已经给总统做了简报。他是实用主义者，他听从了我们。
The Government agrees to lift the ban on the ANC,
政府会同意解除对ANC【非国大】的禁令。
and repeal the race laws. You undertake to renounce violence.
并且废除种族歧视的法律。你要承诺宣布放弃暴力。
No！ But you said...
不！但你说过...
I said nothing.
我什么也没说过。
I listened.
我只倾听。
But you will withdraw your demand for majority rule.
但你会撤消: 你多数人统治的要求。
No.
没有。
Then, what are you giving us in exchange for what we give you?
那么，你打算拿什么来交换我们给予你的一切？
Nothing.
什么都没有。【政治家的本色：谋略！】
These meetings have been a complete waste of our time.
这些会议简直是浪费我们的时间。
Well, I wouldn't say that I wasted my time.
嗯，我不愿说这浪费了我的时间。【四两拔千斤......】
The President has made up his mind. Can't be stopped now.
总统已经作出的决定，不能停止了。
The President is, a member of the Reformer, De Klerk.
总统现为改革家，德克勒克(1936.3.18:78岁）
(1989-1997南非副总统、总统，1993年与曼氏分享诺贝尔和平奖)
very Calvinist.
十足的加尔文教徒。
He believes God calls him to do a special task in a special time.
他坚信上帝召唤他在特殊的时刻完成一项特殊的使命。
After the inauguration service, he wept and said that God was calling him
在总统入职仪式后他流泪说：上帝一直在召唤他
to save the people of South Africa.
来去拯救南非人民。
President De Klerk，
德克勒克总统，【自传记录: 时间1989年12月13日,总统府】
[Boer?]They are here.
【布尔语？】他们在这里。
Please, this way.
这边，请。
Oh, shoe lace!Yeah..
哦，鞋带！好...【戏剧性细节：白人为黑人打鞋带...】
Well, thank you. Well, this is it.
啊，谢谢你。 嗯，就是这儿了。
Mr. Mandela！ Mr. President.
曼德拉先生！总统先生！【相逢一笑泯恩仇......】
May I congratulate you on your election. Thank you.
能让我恭喜你的选举吗？                   谢谢。
【德克勒克1989.9.20大选获胜成为总统,此前为副总统】
You have been called for a very special task...in a very special time.
你被召唤来完成非常特别的使命....在非常特别的时刻。
So I believe.
我就信了。【不管你信不信！】
[Boer]Please sit down.
【布尔语】请坐!
布尔语:南非白人(荷兰人)的语言,又称Afrikaans阿非利卡语/斐语】
You first. Yeah.
您先请。好的。
Mr. Mandela, I've taken the decision to release you
曼德拉先生。我已经做出决定：释放你
unconditionally.
无条件地。
A car will be ready by tomorrow morning to take you to the airport.
明天一大早，有车送你去机场。
A plane will be waiting to fly directly to Johannesburg
会有专机等你，直飞约翰内斯堡
where an Official Release Ceremony will take place.
在那里将举行“官方释放仪式”。
Mr. De Klerk,
德克勒克先生
your people have taken away half of my life
你方人员已剥夺了我大半辈子的生命。
and returned me an old man to a home that's been long abandoned
而把我一个古稀老头扔回给一个被长久遗弃的家庭
and a family that have grown up without me.
并且一家人成长，却从没有我存在。
I don't want you at my side at that moment.
在那一个时刻，我不希望你们在我身边。
I don't want to be told that you have given me my freedom.
我不希望你们通知：你们已经归还了我的自由。
Just open the gate and let me go.
就打开大门，让我走吧。
【英文字幕】1990年2月11日【南非的夏天】
[欢声笑语]
[科萨语...]
[津泽：科萨语密谈...]
Hello...Hello...
你好...你好...
How are you? Hi. I'm good.
你好吗？海。我很好。
I could not do it without you.
没有你，哪有我？【真话：内外联手！】
Do you want me to hold your hand and kiss in the sun？
你要我牵着你的手,在阳光下亲吻？[奔驰是温妮的...]
【英文字幕】约翰内斯堡市奥兰多镇
【1990年2月13日回到8115号故居】
[Poster:VIVA]Somebody wants me!
【标语：万岁!欢迎同志！】有人需要我！
Don't be fooled by all that cheering, Madiba.
不要被所有这些欢呼声中愚弄，马迪巴【曼德拉】。
There's anger out there?
那里还有愤怒？
I know that.
我懂的。
Winnie. Winnie...
温妮！温妮！【对他没有兴趣...】
It's just been too long time.
这一切太长时间了。
It's better that way.
那样也最好。
I'm so tired.
我太累了。
I just want to sleep.
我只想睡个觉。  【没有接受信号。。。】
[焚烧车辆、示威人群]
Singing:Fight the power...
【歌唱：与权力战斗...】
【英文字幕：CODESA1992年5月15日】Convention for a Democratic South Africa CODESA民主南非大会（南非制宪会议，或译南非政协）
The government accepts that change must come.
政府接受必须改变。
But I say to you again,
但我要再次告诉你，
we must find a way to share power.
我们必须找到分享权力的方法。
We must find a way to protect the rights of the minorities
我们必须找到保护少数人权力的方法。
Suddenly the illusion of white power is beginning to crumble.
突然，白人政权的幻觉开始崩溃。
For the first time since apartheid began, the government started talking about the need for reform.
自从种族隔离制度以来，第一次政府开始谈论改革的需求。
Among ordinary white people, feelings now range from bewilderment, anger to fear.
白人平民，人人自危，充满迷惘，愤怒和恐惧。
[Arguing people]
[争论的人群]
Tell me just how do we accept power sharing with the whites?
告诉我吧我们如何分享与白人分享政权？
So what do we do? We fight?
那么，我们该怎么办？我们开战吗？
We start a war? We have a war. Do you think this isn't a war?
我们开战？我们已有场战争。你认为这是不是一战争吗？
We have no war. What we need now is big teeth.
我们现在没有战争。我们需要是强大的效率。
Congress, our people will never accept sharing power with the whites.
ANC会员们，我们的人民永远不会接受与白人分享权力。
They will never accept this. De Klerk should declare...
他们不会接受这点。           德克勒克应该宣布。。。
Why should De Klerk declare what he's already won?
为什么德克勒克应该宣布他已经赢得什么?
He's right! He's right! We must let them share the power.
他是对的。他是对的。我们应该让他们分享权力。
A little power for a little while until the fear has passed.
逐步分享权力，一点点来直到起恐惧消除。
Madiba, I don't think our people will accept that.
阿迪巴，我认为人民不会接受这个办法。
Then we must make them accept. We are their leaders.
我们必须让人民接受。我们是他们的领导。
That is our job.
那是我们的工作。
We come here to speak in just one tone.
我们到此只用一个声音说话。
The games of talking are over.
谈判的游戏现在结束。【标语：要枪...】
Go and get her.
去找她来。
I hear the voice of the people.
我听见人民的呼声，
And that voice says, we will fight!
人民呼吁：我们要战斗！
【口号：VIVA万岁！】曼德拉先生一直在等待。
[人群欢呼雀跃]
What?
怎么了？
Are you ashamed to greet me in front of our people?
你耻于在我们的人民面前问候我吗？
When you speak in public, you must represent the policies of the ANC.
当你在公共场合讲话，你必须代表ANC非国大的各项政策。
What does that mean? we're negotiating?
什么意思? 我们在协商中？
We are not fighting a war. But the people have chosen to fight.
我们不要打仗，但是，人民选择去战斗。
Do you want me to betray our people?
你要我出卖我们的人民吗？
Do I betray our people?
我出卖了我们的人民了？
You have been away a long time...
你离开了很久......
What does that mean "I've been away?" Does that mean now you can terrorize people?
“我离开了很久......”是什么含义？这就意味着你可以恐吓人民吗？
The burning, the necklessness, that has to stop,Winnie!
焚烧，鲁莽, 都必须停止，温妮!
Do you realize there's a war out there?
你意识到外面有场战争吗？
The people are angry. We are all angry.
人民感到愤怒。我们都很生气。
I am angry! You are angry!
我很生气。你很生气！
But you must show loyalty.
但是，你必须表现出忠诚。
Loyalty, Winnie Mandela.
忠诚，温妮・曼德拉。【同志：你还是“我的”人......】
Loyalty！
忠贞！【Loyalty:忠诚于党、忠贞于爱情：双关！】
I've decided that it would be better if I lived in my own home.
我已经决定：最好我住在自己的家里。
better for the party.
对党更好。
better for us.
对我们更好。
better for the party.
对党更好。
You have your own home in Debokrof,
你有自己迪波克鲁夫的家。
You have your own company there.
那里你有自己的伴侣。
Am I to blame because I don't want to be alone?
因为我不想独自一个人生活，就就责怪我？
You know so much of my life? I've been alone.
你对我的生活完全了解，我一直都独自一人生活。
We've both been alone too much, Winnie.
我们俩都“独自”得太久了，温妮.【个性、道路、观念不同：先分居】
Why Walter? Tell me why?
为什么，沃尔特？告诉我为什么？
Why do you show me this?
你为什么要给我看这个？
Do you think I don't know? This has gone too far.
你以为我不知道吗？这已经太过分了。
If she was discrete about this...I have accepted the situation!
如果她分开这一切...我已经接受了现况。
What business is it of anyone else? She's humiliating you in public, Madiba.
这关其他人什么事？她在公共场合侮辱你，马迪巴。
That hits all of us.
那如同打在我们所有人脸上。
Come...
得了。。。
What they have done to my wife is their only victory over me.
【心灵独白】他们给我妻子造成的影响，是他们对我唯一的胜利。
Hello.
大家好。【1992年4月13日记者招待会】
I have a personal statement to make.
我要发布个人申明。
In view of the tensions that have arisen between my wife and myself
鉴于我与妻子间的紧张关系
in the recent months, we have mutually agreed
出现在最近数月里，我们双方一致同意
that a separation would be best for each of us.
分手将会是我们双方最佳选择。
I shall personally never regret the life that we tried to share together.
我个人永远不会后悔：我们曾经努力分担过的生活。
I part from my wife with no recriminations.
我与妻子分离：无怨无悔，没有指责。
I embrace her with all the love and affection
我依然支持她，用我当初全部的热爱、情感,
that I had for her inside and outside prison
我曾在铁窗内外，拥有这份爱,
from the moment I first met her.
而自从我第一次看见她起，就产生了这份爱。【一见钟情】
Ladies and gentlemen I hope you appreciate the pain that I've gone through.
女士们,先生们，我希望你们理解我所经历的这种痛苦。
Police opened fire on gun-carrying demonstrators...
警方向携带武器的抗议者开火，
Nelson Mandela, President De Klerk.
纳尔逊・曼德拉，德克勒克总统。
The situation on the streets is out of control.
街头情况失去控制。
Is this the peace of South Africa you said about?
这就是你所说的南非和平吗？
Black conflict violence has reached proportions of mass civil war.
黑人间的暴力冲突已经达到大规模内战的程度。
They began fighting as the power struggle developed in South Africa
冲突始于南非权力斗争中
to replace white rule with black.
为了用黑人取代白人统治
Some 200 rebels rampaged through a town, cutting down anyone they saw.
大约200名叛军肆虐一个城镇：砍倒他们看到的任何人。
[Screaming]
尖叫声...
[crying]
痛哭...【1992年6月17日博伊帕通惨案：白人政府暗中支持夸祖鲁族激进的因卡塔Inkatha武装黑人员杀死温和的的ANC非国大46人，多数妇女儿童...】
Madiba, do something, give us something for South Africa,
马迪巴【曼德拉】，采取行动吧！为了南非，给我们点东西吧。
we're slipping away, slipping away, do something  , do something.
我们无声地死去，无声地死去，采取行动吧，采取行动吧。
【英文字幕】南非广播公司SABC
[News broadcasting...]
[各种新闻报道]
Mr. Mandela, look at the camera.
曼德拉先生，看镜头。
Movement of light. Provide lighting.
灯光移动，打灯。
[News broadcasting...]..peace process in South Africa...
[各种新闻报道]...南非的和平进程...
[Countdown]5 seconds. 4, 3, 2...
【倒计时】5秒，4，3，2 ...
Someone gave me this note
有人给了我这个纸条
when I was leaving in Boiboton and I want to read it to you.
当时我离开博伊帕通时，我想读给你们
It says... "No peace.
条子上写着：“不要和平。
"Do not talk about peace.
“不要再空谈和平。
"We have had enough. Please, Mr. Mandela.
我们忍受够了。求您了，曼德拉先生。
"No peace.
“不要和平。
"Give us weapons, not peace."
“给我们武器，而不是和平。
This is my answer.
这就是我的答复。
There is only one way forward.
只有一条路: 向前：
And that is peace.
那就是和平。
[人群骚动叫喊]
I know. That is not what you want to hear.
我知道，这不是你们想听到的。
But, there is no other way.
但是，别无选择。
I am your leader.
我是你们的领袖。
And as long as I am your leader, I'm going to give you leadership.
只要我还是你们的领袖，我就会给你【正确】的领导。
As long as I am your leader, I'm going to tell you always when you are wrong.
只要我还是你们的领袖，当你们犯错时，我就总会提醒你们
And I tell you now, you are wrong.
因此我现在告诉你们，你们错了。
I have given my life to this struggle.
我已经把我的生命献给了这场斗争。
I've been willing to die,I've lost 27 years of my life in prison.
我一直愿意为此献身，我已经在铁窗中丧失了我27年生命。
But, I'll tell you now.
但是，我要告诉你们，现在。
I have forgiven now.--[Lie]
现在我已经宽恕了。  --【谎言】
If I can forgive them,then you can forgive them.
如果我都能宽恕他们，那么你也可以宽恕他们。
We can not win a war.
我们不可能赢得了战争。
But, we can win an election.
但是，我们可能赢得了选举。
So, my people,
所以，我的同胞们，
Stay home,
留在家里。
Be peaceful.
保持和平。
And when election day comes,
而当选举日到来的时候，
vote.
投票。
That's it!
就这样!
【英文字幕】你可以在他领导下服务吗？
是的，我能。开弓没有回头箭。就这么开始了。
After so much suffering, why would anyone believe that...
【心灵独白】历经这么多痛苦之后，为什么有人愿意相信
putting their mark on a piece of paper,is going to change the world?
在一张纸上打个勾，就会改变世界？
【英语字幕】1994年4月27日 新南非大选日
"My yoyage" is a South African song,
《MV VoVage我的航行》是南非首歌曲,
and it's simply a plea to all South Africans,to come together to share their problems,
它就是呼吁全体南非人民，团结起来，一起分担问题，
try to solve them, in the manner and fashion of our forefathers and kings....The words simply means: Come back, Africa!
努力解决问题，用我们的祖先和国王的方式与风格。。。。歌词就是：回来吧，非洲！。
【南非说唱】...回到1944年那首南非歌曲...
【字幕：庆祝ANC获胜】1994年5月10日曼德拉就职新南非首任总统
Olishasha...I still dream the old dream:
奥利沙沙...我仍然做着那个旧梦:
back in the house in Orlando，
回到奥兰多8115号的老房子，
I can hear all the ones that I've loved most in the world,
我能听见我在这个世界上我的至爱们。
I want to reach them,
我想要向他们伸出手，
to touch them,
去爱抚他们，
but they have gone.
但他们都已经离去了。
Dad
爸爸【如梦似幻...】
Madiba, you ready for this?
马迪巴【曼德拉】，你准备好了吗？
These are my jailers now.
现在，这些人是我的看守了。【jailer与journalist(新闻业者)近音】
暗指：南非新闻自由独立于立法、司法和行政,成为第四权力。
They're so proud of you, Mr. Mandela. Yes, Ma'am...
他们真为你感到骄傲，曼德拉先生。是的，夫人...
【首都比勒托利亚,1994年5月10日,曼德拉就任新南非总统】
他是300多年来南非首位黑人民选总统，和平终结维护少数白人统治的种族隔离制度
I have walked a long walk to freedom.
【心灵独白】我走了漫漫长路, 来争取自由。【如梦似幻...】
It has been a long road.
这是一条漫长的道路。【故中译自传名：漫漫自由路】
And it is not over yet.
但是，这还没有结束。
【南非的贫富分化和种族和解影响社会治安、政治平稳、经济发展......】
【1943-1994:约52年.1994年12月17日曼德拉自传《漫漫自由路》正式出版发行，1998放弃连任机会。】
I know that my country was not made to be a land of hatred.
我知道，我的国家没有缔造成为充满仇恨的土地
【非洲无种族灭绝，没有政变，没有军人执政、没有世袭特权的国家：南非！】
No one is born hating another person
无人生而仇恨他人
because of the color of his skin.
只因为他皮肤的颜色。
People learn to hate,
人们是学会仇恨的，
they can be taught to love
人们也能学会去爱
for love comes more naturally
因为爱产生自然
to the human heart.
爱源自人心。【人之初, 性本善: 博爱】
【南非的民主政治制度是其保证：祝福南非人民！】
南非是非洲最欧化、最富裕、最强大的国家，BRIC金砖四国之一。
别走开：请欣赏2014年71届金球奖最佳原创歌曲的主题曲
Ordinary Love 平凡的爱【英国U2乐队】
《曼德拉：漫漫自由路》
此曲积极向上，传达了传奇人物曼德拉充满爱的自由观：
自由，不仅是不惧肉身的囚禁，更是有能力越出仇恨的心狱。
The sea wants to kiss the golden shore
大海想要亲吻金色沙滩
The sunlight warms your skin
阳光温暖着你的肌肤
All the beauty that's been lost before
曾经失落的所有美好
wants to find us again
都想要再回到我们身边
I can't fight you anymore
我无法再与你战斗
It's you I'm fighting for
你就是我战斗的理由
The sea throws rocks together
大海将岩石冲一起
But time leaves us polished stones
但时光却为我们留下光滑的石头
We can't fall any further
我们无法再深沉陷入爱河
If we can't feel ordinary love
若我们不能感受这平凡的爱
We cannot reach any higher
我们无法达到更高
If we can't deal with ordinary love
若我们无法处理这平凡的爱
Birds fly high in the summer sky
鸟儿翱翔在夏日天空
And rest on the breeze
在微风中滑翔
The same wind will take care of you and
一样的风也将吹拂你，而
I will build our house in the trees
我要建我们的家建在树上
Your heart is on my sleeve
我的袖口印着你的心
Did you put it there with a magic marker
你用魔法印在那里吗
For years I would believe
多年来我一直相信
That the world couldn't wash it away
全世界永远也不能冲刷走那颗心
'Cause we can't fall any further
因为我们无法再深沉陷入爱河
If we can't feel ordinary love
若我们无法感受这平凡的爱
【非高清版：演职人员表完全不清晰！】
We cannot reach any higher
我们无法到达更高
If we can't deal with ordinary love
若我们无法处理这平凡的爱
Are we tough enough
我们是否足够强悍
For ordinary love
来承受这平凡之爱
We can't fall any further
我们无法再深沉陷入爱河
If we can't feel ordinary love
若我们不能感受这平凡的爱
We cannot reach any higher
我们无法达到更高
If we can't deal with ordinary love
若我们不能处理这平凡的爱
Are we tough enough
我们是否足够强悍
For ordinary love
来承受这平凡之爱
Are we tough enough
我们是否足够强悍
For ordinary love
来承受这平凡之爱
Are we tough enough
我们是否足够强悍
For ordinary love
来承受这平凡之爱
致敬!坚毅的民主自由斗士、当代政治思想家：曼德拉1918.7.18－2013.12.5享年95岁
[听译、校对0202、配歌词及时间轴Penguin:342635392@qq.com.]
Olishasha...Olishasha...